A Guide to the State Council of Higher Education for Virginia. Office of the Director. Subject and Correspondence Files, 1974-1997
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
State Council of Higher Education for Virginia. Office of the Director. Subject and Correspondence Files, 1974-1997
Library of Virginia
36681
7.5 cu. ft.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred 30 June 1999.
Biographical/Historical Information
The State Council of Higher Education for Virginia was created by an act of the General Assembly on March 10, 1956, to act as the state's coordinating and advising body for institutions of higher education. The purpose of the Council is to promote the development and operation of an educationally and economically sound, vigorous, progressive, and coordinated system of education in the Commonwealth. Among the Council's significant responsibilities are: to develop a master plan for higher education and to conduct other planning activities; to establish guidelines for operating and capital outlay budgets of the institutions of higher education and to review and to make recommendations on budget requests to the Governor and General Assembly; to approve changes in institutional missions; to approve any new degree programs; to terminate non-productive degree programs; approve enrollment projections of the institutions; to grant approval to in-state, private institutions to confer degrees; to involve the private and proprietary institutions to confer degrees; to involve the private and proprietary institutions in the state's overall planning for postsecondary institutions in the state's overall planning for postsecondary education; to administer statewide student financial assistance programs; to provide guidelines for determining the domiciliary residence of students applying for in-state tuition rates; to establish and revise, as necessary, guidelines for patent and copyright policies developed by the public institutions; to coordinate the continuing education offerings of the public institutions; and to develop guidelines for the assessment of student achievement. The Council consists of eleven members appointed by the governor, subject to confirmation by the General Assembly.
Dr. Gordon K. Davies served as the Assistant Director of SCHEV from 1974 to 1977 and Director of SCHEV from 1977-1997. Dr. Davies is credited with having guided the state-supported institutions within the Commonwealth of Virginia to new levels of excellence. His tenure as Director ended in April 1997 when the Council voted to not renew his contract. The Council's move to release Dr. Davies was controversial and prompted the resignation of several Council members.
Scope and Content Information
Comprised of the administrative papers of Dr. Gordon K. Davies, Director of the State Council of Higher Education (SCHEV), 1977-1997. Contains correspondence, speeches, publications, reports, newsclippings and other materials related to Dr. Davies' activities as director. Also included in the collection is documentation regarding his activities outside of SCHEV as a member of the Desegregation Settlement Compliance Committee for the Louisiana Board of Regents, an evaluator of the Kentucky Centers of Excellence and Endowed Chairs, and as a member of a National Governor's Association group that travelled to Nepal to study the institutions of higher education in that country. Documentation regarding the working dynamics of the agency are primarily found in electronic correspondence.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: I. Correspondence; II. Speeches and writings; III. External activities; IV. Termination as Director of SCHEV; V. Gordon K. Davies; and VI. Miscellaneous Materials.
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence, 1975-1997
  Divided into three (3) subseries: General Correspondence; Electronic Correspondence; and Letters of Reference. All correspondence is arranged chronologically, and are described individually.
  - Subseries 1: General Correspondence, 1975-1997
    Arrange chronologically by date. Contains routine correspondence regarding issues in higher education as well as correspondence regarding Dr. Davies' speaking engagements.
    - Correspondence, 1975-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, nd (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 2: Electronic Correspondence, 1986-1995 (bulk 1987-1989)
    Arranged chronologically by the beginning date of the messages in the printout. Contains local area network (LAN) messages on the PROFS system as well as electronci mail (e-mail) with individuals outside SCHEV and institutions of higher education in the Commonwealth. Some printouts overlap in date and content, and some printouts are incomplete. Some messages have been blocked out due to privacy-protected subjects, resulting in blank spots on some pages.
    - Electronic Correspondence, July 28-August 1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Electronic Correspondence, September 2-December 18, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Electronic Correspondence, December 18, 1987-January 15, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Electronic Correspondence, December 21, 1987-January 15, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Electronic Correspondence, December 31, 1987-May 30, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Electronic Correspondence, January 4-14, 1988; January 4-February 3, 1988--see box 8 folder 1, legal size (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Electronic Correspondence, January 15, 1988; January 15-February 2, 1988--see box 8 folder 2, legal size (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Electronic Correspondence, February 1-24, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Electronic Correspondence, February 4-March 7, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Electronic Correspondence, February 25-March 26, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Electronic Correspondence, March 9-25, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Electronic Correspondence, March 29-April 20, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Electronic Correspondence, April 5-May 4, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Electronic Correspondence, April 21-26, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Electronic Correspondence, May 2-18, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Electronic Correspondence, May 4-26, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Electronic Correspondence, May 11-October 3, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Electronic Correspondence, May 19-June 15, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Electronic Correspondence, May 26-June 7, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Electronic Correspondence, June 8-17, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Electronic Correspondence, June 8-July 13, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Electronic Correspondence, June 19-July 13, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Electronic Correspondence, July 14-August 9, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Electronic Correspondence, August 5-September 1, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Electronic Correspondence, August 5-September 2, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Electronic Correspondence, August 30-September 30, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Electronic Correspondence, September 1-October 14, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Electronic Correspondence, September 12-October 26, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Electronic Correspondence, October 8-10, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Electronic Correspondence, October 8-26, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Electronic Correspondence, October 13-November 28, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Electronic Correspondence, October 26-December 2, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Electronic Correspondence, December 1, 1988-January 30, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Electronic Correspondence, January 24-April 24, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Electronic Correspondence, February 8-April 21, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Electronic Correspondence, May 4-June 14, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Subseries 3: Letters of Reference, 1985-1996
    Contains letters and resumes of individuals requesting that Dr. Davies be a reference for job-seeking purposes. Some return correspondence from Dr. Davies is also included. Correspondence is generally grouped by individual and arranged chronologically. Some items have been removed or have had sections blocked out due to privacy issues. The last folder of this series contains requests from Dr. Davies requesting references for and responses to nominations for his own employment searches.
    - Correspondence, References and Nominations, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Correspondence, References and Nominations, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Correspondence, References and Nominations, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Correspondence, References and Nominations, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Correspondence, References and Nominations, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Correspondence, References and Nominations, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Correspondence, References and Nominations, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Correspondence, References and Nominations, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Correspondence, References and Nominations, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, References and Nominations, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, References and Nominations, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, References and Nominations, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, References and Nominations, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, References and Nominations, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, References and Nominations, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, References and Nominations, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, References and Nominations, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Series II: Speeches and Writings, 1974-1997
  Arranged into four (4) subseries: Speeches given by Dr. Davies; Speeches given by others; Writings and Publications; and Source Materials. Items are arranged chronologically within each series. Each subseries is described individually.
  - Subseries 1: Speeches given by Dr. Davies, 1975-1997
    Arranged chronologically by date of event. Includes remarks made at convocations and commencements at state-supported institutions throughout the Commonwealth; speeches made at professional conferecnes, meetings of community organizations; and other events. Source materials for speeches are located in Series IV.
    - Virginia Association of Economists, April 4, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - SRED Legislative Work Conference, July 30, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Education in Virginia: Problems and Promises, March 12, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Association of Virginia Colleges, March 31, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Madison College Commencement Address, May 7, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University Administrative Conference, September 6, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Virginia Association of Student Financial Aid Administrators Fall Meeting, September 28, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Virginia Community College System Annual Meeting, November 11, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Articulation Conference, November 22, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Norfolk State College Faculty Convocation, January 9, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Association of Virginia Colleges, January 18, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Fund for the Improvement of Post-Secondary Education (FIPSE), January 19, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Summer School Deans, April 71, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Council of Visitors, April 24, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Association of Institutional Research, May 25, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Central Virginia Community College Commencement, June 10, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Longwood College Convocation, September 7, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Roanoke Rotary, September 27, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Petersburg Rotary, October 12, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Virginia Community College System Annual Meeting, November 10, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Virginia Association of Collegiate Registrars and Admission Officers, December 11, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Richmond Kiwanis Club December 18, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Winchester Rotary Club, January 11, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Petersburg Kiwanis Club, January 16, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Association of Virginia Colleges, January 31, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - State Pre-Planning Conference on Education and Career Information and Referral Services in Virginia, March 7, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Virginia Association for Biological Education, March 30, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Virginia Commonwealth University Faculty Forum, April 5, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Curry School of Education Convocation, University of Virginia, April 6, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - George Washington University Inauguration of President George W. Johnson, April 7, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Annual Meeting of Council of Visitors University of Virginia, April 23, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Old Dominion University Commencement, May 12, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Clinch Valley College Commencement, May 27, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - New River Community University College Commencement, June 8, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Southern Regional Education Board (SREB) Legislative Work Conference, August 10, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Roanoke Rotary Club, September 27, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Workshop for American Council on Education (ACE) Annual Meeting, October 31, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Virginia Community College System Annual Meeting, November 9, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Conference for Potential Minority Graduate Students, November 30, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - 1st Annual Forum on Education Clinch Valley College of the University of Virginia, December 17, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Richard Bland College Commencement, May 18, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Emory and Henry College Commencement, May 31, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Blue Ridge Community College Commencement, June 15, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Piedmont Community College Faculty Convocation, September 16, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Governor's Orientation Workshop for College and University Board Members, October 15, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Statement to the House Education Committee Regarding HJR 254, February 2, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Centennial Symposium--Bridgewater College, April 1, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Old Dominion University Developmental Writing Workshop, April 24, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Shenandoah College Commencement, April 26, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Mountain Empire Community College Commencement, June 12, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Tidewater Community College Commencement, June 14, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - NASSGP/NCHELP Joint Conference, October 28, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Conference for Potential Minority Graduate Students, November 13, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Council of Graduate Schools Annual Workshop, December 1, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Virginia Business Council, December 4, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Virginia Women's Studies Association, December 5, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - 1982 Student-Legislator Forum, March 26, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Military Education Conference, April 1, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Hollins Collge, October 29, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Conference for Potential Minority Graduate Students, November 5, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Seminar-"Politics and Higher Administration" December 10, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Governor's Commission on Virginia's Future, March 3, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Congressional Breakfast, May 3, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS) Panel: Future of Research Universities, May 31, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Inservice Education Program of the State Higher Education Executive Officers (SHEEO) and the Education Commission of the States (ECS), August 10, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Inservice Education Program of the State Higher Education Executive Officers (SHEEO) and the Education Commission of the States (ECS), August 12, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - "A Program to Ensure Educational Opportunity to Virginia's Workforce", May 20, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Virginia Consortium for Professional Psychology, August 27, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - University of Southern California, Washington D.C. Commencement, September 18, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Planning for Educational Mobility for Registered Nurses in Virginia, September 20, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Academic Affiars Administrators, Southeastern Regional Conference, October 7, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - Virginia Consortium for Asian Studies, October 8, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - George Mason University Symposium on International Cultural Perspectives in Literature and Language, November 4, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - Statewide Workshop on Student Retention, November 6, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - Conference for Potential Graduate Students, November 11, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - National Association of State Universities of Land Grant Colleges (NASULGC) Council on Extension and Continuing Education, November 14, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Virginia Commonwealth University Honors Program Convocation, November 18, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Commonwealth Conference on Education, November 27, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - "Policy Planning and Finances of Virginia Higher Education"--House Appropriations Committee, December 19, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Southside Virginia Community College Honors Conference, May 3, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Southwest Virginia Community College Commencement, June 13, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Council of Higher Education Budget Conference, June 14, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - State Higher Education Executive Officers Annual Meeting, August 1, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Food for Thought Program--Virginia Commonwealth University, November 13, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Seminar for Board of Visitors, December 20, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Shenandoah College--Convocation on Curriculum, May 13, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Annual Summer Professional Development Workshops University of Virginia Center for the Study of Higher Educaiton, June 16, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Notes for Speeches-- see box 8 folder 3, legal size -- Governor's School of Sceince and Technology, August 28, 1985; James Madison University Faculty Convocation, August 30, 1985; Virginia Electrical League, September 16, 1985
    - Conference for Potential Graduate Students, November 8, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - National Invitational Conference on State and Federal Policy Affecting Adult Learners, November 17, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Virginia Military Institute Foundation, May 14, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - North Cross School, June 6, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Knowledge for the New Econoly: Higher Educaiton and Small Business, June 12, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Virginia Community College System Leadership SEminar, June 18, 1986 (see box 8 folder 4, legal size); Virginia Commonwealth University Mathematics Colloquium, June 26, 1986 (see box 8 folder 5, legal size)
    - Governor's Conference on Education, July 23, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Virginia Association of Student Financial Aid Administrators, September 29, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Radford University--Arts and Sciences Convocation, October 17, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Meeting of Graudate Deans, College of William and Mary, October 27, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Articulation Conference, October 30, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Conference for Potential Graduate Students, November 6, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Conference on the Academic Profession, November 6, 1986 (see box 8 folder 6, legal size); North Central Association--Wingspread Symposium, November 19, 1986 (see box 8 folder 7, legal size)
    - Dean's Colloquia, Christopher Newport College, December 3, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Indiana University-Purdue University at Fort Wayne, December 16, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Hampton University Winter Faculty Institute, January 12, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - American Association for Higher Education Black Caucus, March 2, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Virginia Commonwealth University Forbes Day Activities, March 5, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Randolph-Macon College Board of Associates, March 20, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - SCHEV Statewide Conference on Black Student Retention, March 29, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - North Central Association of College and Schools (see also:North Central Association--Wingspread Symposium, November 19, 1986), April 12, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Conference on Video Resources in Virginia, May 29, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Virginia Community College System Leadership Seminar, June 23, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - White House Conference on Libraries and Information Services Technologies, August 27, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - House Subcommittee on Postsecondary Education, September 15, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Tidewater Community College, September 17, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Governor's Conference on Employment and Training, September 22, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Virginia Community College System Instructional Leadership Seminar, September 23, 1987 (see box 8 folder 8, legal size)
    - Conference of Visitors, October 21, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Virginia Association for Management and Planning, November 16, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Association of Governing Boards, January 20, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - College of William and Mary Board of Visitors, February 5, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Richmond Rotary, March 8, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Virginia Association of Independent Schools, April 5, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Virginia Wesleyan College Annual Dinner of the Baord of Trustees, April 13, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Longwood College Honors Banquet, April 14, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University Honors Banquet, April 20, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Virginia Association for Cooperative Education, April 21, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Board of Visitors--Mary Washington College, April 22, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Averett College, April 30, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Statewide Conference on Black Student Retention, May 1, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Center for Adhesion Science, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, May 3, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - University of Virginia Board of Visitors' Meeting, May 26, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Virginia Community College System Leadership Seminar, June 23, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 51)